Today we're going to look at Salt and
Straws Cocoa Peppermint, but basically
this is peppermint patty ice cream with
a twist. [music]
Yep. Looking through the recipe books, I
wanted to do a seasonal flavor. Uh, you
know, I guess Halloween is next week.
Um, or this weekend and next is
Christmas, so I'm going to do a
Christmas one because I want to. Um,
peppermint patty is, if for those that
don't know, is basically like um a
peppermint paste wrapped in chocolate. I
think Hershey's own the York brand. Um,
so the chocolate is going to be
Hershey's chocolate.
Uh, those in England and Europe, you
can't get these. But if you think of
like an After Eight that hasn't had
enough amalayise in it and it isn't
soft, it's quite hard stick. That's kind
of what it is. So, the peppermint
patties aren't soft um semi liquid
peppermint core. They're still really
tasty. Salt and Straw have got their
cocoa peppermint, which is their
standard base plus cocoa with homemade
peppermint patties inside, but I wanted
to kind of switch this up a little bit.
So, I'm going to do their cocoa base
using their methods for ice cream, but
I'm going to do a peppermint patty core.
So, a peppermint center core to this.
So, sounds delicious. What are we going
to need for the Salt and Straw standard
ice cream base? You're going to need 110
g or half a cup of granulated sugar, 30
g or 2 tbsp of skim milk powder, 1.2 2 g
or 1/4 teaspoon of zantham gum, 30 g or
2 tbsps of light corn syrup, 332 g or 1
and a3 cups of whole milk, and 332 g or
1 and a3 cups of heavy cream. For the
addition to that, you're going to need
55 g or 1/4 cup of granulated sugar, 30
g or 1/4 cup of unsweetened cocoa
powder. So, this is just standard cocoa
powder, not drinking chocolate. Okay? uh
five grams of mint extract or one drop
of peppermint oil and then obviously
your ice cream base above. So the way
Salt and Straw work in their recipe
books is they create a generalized ice
cream base and then they add to it for
every recipe to create something
different. With that in mind, we're then
going to make our peppermint core. We
got a few things to make here. It's not
particularly complicated. Let's get on
and make the base.
So, according to the recipe book, we
need to add, so we're just dealing with
the ice cream base for now, the
standardized base, the salt and straw
do. We need to add our sugar, our skim
milk powder, and our zantham gum into a
small pot and stir it together. So,
let's do that.
110 g of sugar,
30 g of skin milk powder, 1.2 g of
zantham gum. Let's get our tiny whisk
and we're going to give that a stir
together. Stirring again to break up our
stabilizer. Santh being a cold processed
stabilizer, salt and straw heat it up.
They don't superheat it. They just heat
the base to dissolve the sugars. So
there's that there. The next stage is in
this pan we have our 30 g of corn syrup.
We're going to add in our 332 g of milk.
And it says to stir that together.
That's going to be tough because it's
not going to do absolutely anything
until we get it on the heat. So it then
says to add in our milk powder, sugar,
zantham gum mixture. So in that goes.
And then we're going to heat this up
gently. I'm reading the instructions as
we go. Heat this up gently to dissolve
the sugars. Then we take it off the
heat. So let's do that. It should only
take a few minutes to dissolve the
sugar. Really doesn't need to be heated
too high. So just be gentle.
Okay. just a couple of minutes to
completely dissolve or or loosen up and
incorporate that corn syrup. So, with
that on there, we're going to add in our
cream, which is 332 g as well.
And that is our salt and straw base.
That's the simplified base
that everything in this recipe book
anyway uses.
So, we can put that in a container.
And that is now going to go in the
fridge. It says at least 6 hours,
preferably 24 hours. So let's leave this
for 24 hours in a refrigerator and then
we'll move on to the next bit. So with
that now chilling now in there, we're
going to prepare the next part, which is
the cocoa part, the chocolate part that
will eventually get added to that. But
in the recipe book, it says to prepare
this independently and chill it down and
mix it together when it's completely
cold. So, let's do what it says in the
book.
We put our sugar in here. 55 g of our
sugar.
And then in the instructions, it says to
add in 1/4 cup of water, which is not in
the ingredients list. So, 1/4 cup of
water. 1/4 of a cup of water, which is
45 g. And we need to bring it to a boil
apparently, and then immediately take it
off the heat. So, let's do that. a nice
rapid
boil. So, nice and quick, super fast.
Now, it says to add in our cocoa butter.
Cocoa butter. Cocoa powder. So, that's
30 g of cocoa powder. And stir it in
quickly.
That's a really piss poor way of dealing
with cocoa powder. But there you go.
Then it says we're going to need to let
that cool down to, you know, room
temperatureish before we add in our mint
extract. So, let's leave it here for
about half an hour. That will cool it
down enough so that we don't burn off
the volatile flavor compounds that are
in our extract. So, come back when we're
ready to do that. So, I've just cooled
this down quickly over some cold water.
And
I have peppermint extract rather than
oil. So,
I'm going to put a little bit more on
cuz I I personally don't think 5 g
um or one drop of peppermint oil is
anywhere near enough. Going to put this
in a little container
like so. And now this can go in the
refrigerator. So, the peppermint patty
core, I'm going to make that first thing
in the morning when this comes out ready
to churn because we're going to mix our
two component ice cream base together.
We're going to churn it. We're going to
pop it back in the freezer for about an
hour to firm up enough so that we can
get our core shape in the middle. And
whilst that's hardening up in the
freezer for that to happen, we'll make
our peppermint patty core and add it in
then. So, see you in the morning.
The recipe called to keep them in the
refrigerator overnight or you know
minimum six up to 24 hours. 24 hours for
a better flavor. So that's what I've
done. I think this chocolate addin is
going to be too hard straight out of the
refrigerator. So might have to Yeah. I
mean it's way too hard to mix into that
base. I don't know why they suggested
that. Way, way too hard.
So, I'm going to stir this and try and
loosen it back up so that it would
actually be mixable. If you try this
recipe, don't keep this chocolate in the
in the refrigerator like they suggest in
the recipe book. It's just it's too hard
to successfully reinccorporate into that
base. So,
30 seconds of mixing this back up.
That's about as thin as it's going to
get without actually heating it up. So,
let's combine it all.
Whisk it all together. This is going to
take a little bit. So, all right. Well,
it actually didn't take too long. Took
about a minute to completely incorporate
that back in. Our machine is now
pre-chilled. So, let's get this in here.
We'll cut to some music. And I'll load
this into the tubs and put it in the
freezer
for about an hour, maybe two, depending
on uh how well it freezes cuz we want it
a little bit harder so that we can
create that core in the middle. So,
let's do that. So, churn your ice cream
as normal. And this base actually does
look pretty silky and smooth to be fair.
And when it comes time to loading up,
you're not going to fill your tubs up
completely because we're going to make a
core section in the center. So if you
overfill then you might have to take
some out
right now. So that's now in the freezer
just hardening off a little bit. If you
try and make the core while it's just
been shown it's too soft then the core
fills in. So we need to just harden it
off just a little bit so that we can
actually create that gap for our
peppermint core. If you hear some noise
outside, it's that time of year. It's
seasonal tire swap. So I use a great
local company. They come out and swap my
tires, but it is noisy. So that's
probably what you'll hear. I got a
little bit of leftover ice cream.
Our peppermint core. We are making a
peppermint, very traditional peppermint
soft fondant. Um, we are going to need
240 g of condensed milk. You're also
going to need 200 g of powdered sugar or
icing sugar. 30 g or thereabouts of
water. We'll talk about that as we do
it. And then our peppermint extract. Use
as much or as little as you want. And
finally, just a little pinch of salt
just to balance that flavor out. So,
let's get our condensed milk. 240 grams.
And into that, we're going to put our
water. There's noise coming everywhere
at the moment. So, we're going to put 30
g of water in here.
30 g is enough to kind of loosen it up.
That's really what the water is for,
just to loosen this up so that it
remains either pipable or porable,
however you're going to put it in. We're
going to put this on a hob and just heat
this up. We're not going to super heat
this up. Please do not boil this. We
need to maintain that water level in
here. So, on the hob, heat it up 4050
degrees centigrade, then stop. Literally
only took a couple of minutes. We're
just actually just thinning that
condensed milk down so that everything
else can incorporate. We're not really
doing anything to it apart from that.
And actually, the amount of condensed
milk turns out about 2/3 of that can. So
into that we're going to add our 200 g
of So whilst I'm incorporating this
powdered sugar into our condensed milk
and water. If you want it to go slightly
harder in the freezer then use less
water. So in this recipe I use 30 g. You
know you can probably reduce that by
half if you really want to and it will
go quite hard. It might not be as
scoopable or spoonable. If you like it
really loose and runny, then add another
15 g of water to it. You'll be able to
pour that in with ease and it will
probably pour out to be fair. It won't
freeze
solid at all. This I personally found
this a really good balance, a really
good mix um of a core that you can scoop
with your ice cream but will also start
flowing if you give it, you know, 10 15
seconds. So, just going to get any
remaining little lumps out of there. In
goes our peppermint extract.
That's about half a teaspoon.
One teaspoon.
One and a half teaspoons. About two
teaspoons. I like my peppermint. I like
my flavors as a whole strong. Nice
strong smell. Finally, just a touch of
salt. Make sure it's nice and fine.
Now, what we're going to do is I'm going
to use a piping bag.
That's going to go in there. And
I'm going to put this in the
refrigerator to completely cool down
whilst the ice cream is chilling down
for that next hour.
Salt and straw, peppermint patty base.
My own mint peppermint patty core.
That mint core, perfect texture, kind of
oozing out the middle slowly, even at
freezer temperatures. Uh, I wanted it to
do that. I didn't want it so hard that
when you scoop it, you kind of hit it in
the middle. This is delicious. I mean, I
wish it had a little bit more chocolate
flavor in the base. That's me being
picky, you know. Um, I used I used Dan
Cocoa powder. They're a Dutch company
that originally Anyway, that's where the
company started. So, yeah, I wish this
had a little bit more cocoa forward
flavor. the the process of making this
is a real faf if you're just going to
experiment with ice creams and different
methods because you wouldn't ordinarily
create the two individual parts, let
them chill and then mix them together.
It's definitely a Christmy kind of
flavor and mint chocolate is always
associated with Christmas. I don't know
why. I love Christmas. Every year I
dress up as Santa Claus just like this
for my daughter and for other kids in
the town and just because I love
Christmas. So, hope you enjoyed this
video. Thanks very much for watching.
Don't forget to like and subscribe. I'm
going to choose one of your suggestions
that was in the comments of last week's
video for next week. And I will see you
next week.